Guide to the Alfred Stieglitz / Georgia O'Keeffe Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alfred Stieglitz / Georgia O'Keeffe archive
1728-1986
1880-1986
YCAL MSS 85
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
168
(260 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 10 art
The Alfred Stieglitz/Georgia O'Keeffe Archive contains correspondence files, manuscripts, documentary ephemera, photographs, art and realia related to the lives and careers of Alfred Stieglitz and Georgia O'Keeffe, his second wife, and to other members of Stieglitz's family. The first subgroup, Alfred Stieglitz Papers, consists of material documenting Stieglitz's life's work: correspondence with artists, photographers, and writers; manuscripts by Stieglitz and others describing the art movements of the early twentieth century; scrapbooks; an autograph collection; prints of photographs by Stieglitz and other noted photographers; awards given to Stieglitz for his work; several works of art such as four poster portraits by Charles Demuth; and notebooks assembled posthumously to record the contents of Stieglitz's extensive art collection before it was dispersed following his death. The second subgroup, Georgia O'Keeffe Papers, consists primarily of correspondence from O'Keeffe's friends and family along with a number of fan letters, subject files, and business correspondence addressing rights and reproductions of O'Keeffe's works. This subgroup also includes files of documentary ephemera and a number of awards and medals given to O'Keeffe. The third subgroup, Stieglitz Family Papers, consists of correspondence, documentary ephemera, and drawings from Stieglitz family members, principally Alfred's parents, Edward and Hedwig.
Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946
O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1887-1986
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired as gifts and purchases from the Stieglitz Estate and the Stieglitz family, Georgia O'Keeffe, the O'Keeffe Estate, and other parties. For further information, please see the History of the Archive.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 104-105: Restricted fragile material. Microfilm is available. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 146: Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator.
Box 146: for research use only. May not be duplicated.
Boxes 247-256: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 257: Restricted fragile material. All material has been digitized. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Alfred Stieglitz / Georgia O'Keeffe Collection (YCAL MSS 104) and Flora Stieglitz Strauss Collection of Stieglitz Family Papers (YCAL MSS 89).
Existence and Location of Copies
A portion of this collection is also available on microfilm. See Appendix Five for details.
History of the Archive
The Alfred Stieglitz/Georgia O'Keeffe Archive contains correspondence files, manuscripts, documentary ephemera, photographs, art and realia related to the lives and careers of photographer/publisher/gallery owner Alfred Stieglitz (1864-1946) and painter Georgia O'Keeffe (1886-1986), his second wife. After Stieglitz's death in 1946, Georgia O'Keeffe sought to collect all of his personal and professional correspondence and papers, clipping files, scrapbooks, exhibition-related material and other documentary evidence. The estate employed two women, Dorothy Norman (through 1949) and Doris Bry (from 1949), on projects to organize the correspondence and other files, and to gather letters (or copies of letters) that Stieglitz had written to others.
In 1948, Carl Van Vechten suggested to O'Keeffe that she place the Stieglitz archive at the Yale University Library, where it would join other important Modernist writers' and artists' papers in the Yale Collection of American Literature. O'Keeffe visited New Haven in April 1949 and subsequently made arrangements for the transfer of the collection. The bulk of the material arrived in shipments received between 1949 and 1953 by way of Doris Bry, who worked with O'Keeffe in New York and New Mexico to organize Stieglitz's files and to help select art and photographs for inclusion in the archive.
To accompany this core group of Stieglitz materials, between 1953 and 1980 the Yale library acquired additional Stieglitz and Stieglitz-related items from various other sources, through gift, purchase or by exchange, including hundreds of letters or copies of letters written by Stieglitz to his many friends, family and associates. In addition, a significant body of Stieglitz family papers was received by the library for the archive as the gift of Flora Stieglitz Straus and Sue Davidson Lowe. (Additional information about the history and scope of the Alfred Stieglitz Papers may be found in an article written by Doris Bry for The Yale University Library Gazette, vol. 25, no. 4, April 1951). In addition, the library acquired many of O'Keeffe's papers, which she intended to be added to Stieglitz's papers in order to eventually create what she titled the "Alfred Stieglitz/Georgia O'Keeffe Archive." Portions were received from the artist during her lifetime, and the remainder was transferred to the library in 1992 from the Georgia O'Keeffe Foundation, in accordance with the terms of her will.
All of the material acquired between 1949 and 1980, whether from O'Keeffe or the Stieglitz family, or as the result of O'Keeffe's efforts to document Stieglitz's life and work, plus the O'Keeffe papers transferred to the library by the O'Keeffe Foundation, were combined by the library for the Alfred Stieglitz/Georgia O'Keeffe Archive. Other Stieglitz, O'Keeffe and Stieglitz/O'Keeffe-related materials acquired since 1980 are treated as separately cataloged, corollary accessions, not as part of the archive.
Over the years library staff members, as well as O'Keeffe's personal assistants, listed or otherwise arranged portions of the Stieglitz papers, but the archive as a whole was not processed until 1994-1996, when it was organized into three distinct subgroups: Alfred Stieglitz Papers (Series I-VII), the Georgia O'Keeffe Papers (Series VIII-X), and the Stieglitz Family Papers (Series XI) and fully described in a single finding aid for the Alfred Stieglitz/Georgia O'Keeffe Archive (YCAL MSS 85).
Scope and Contents
Alfred Stieglitz Papers (Series I-VII) The Alfred Stieglitz Papers (Boxes 1-176) have been organized into seven series: Series I. Correspondence (personal, professional, and family letters); Series II. Manuscripts (primarily written for his publishing projects); Series III. Documentary Ephemera (his scrapbooks, clipping files, publications of his galleries, and an autograph collection); Series IV. Photographs (by and of him, his family and associates); Series V. Awards; Series VI. Works of Art (that which O'Keeffe determined was more of a documentary nature, less of fine art); and Series VII. Art Collection Notebooks, which document Stieglitz's art and sculpture collection and record its distribution to museums after his death.
Absent from Stieglitz's papers, however, is much of the other standard ephemera of personal life, such as school records, personal diaries, financial records, passports or medical records. Two account statements from the Shelton Hotel are filed in Series I, and a five-page "journal" from 1873 can be found with his writings in Series II, as can his commonplace book of 1884. A file of miscellaneous receipts can be found at the end of his correspondence files. Perhaps of greater significance, also lacking are any formal business records from his decades of work as a purveyor of photography and art. While some actual financial documents do exist in the correspondence files (account sheets for the firm of George Of, some deposit slips for Guaranty Trust Company, and a few rent receipts from George R. Read, for example), and there is one folder containing cancelled checks (made out to individuals, largely artists) at the end of Series I, there are no official business records such as check registers, ledger books, personnel files or inventories.
These lacunae are real, obvious and unfortunate, particularly for those hoping to be able to create a picture of Stieglitz's business acumen or to document the sales of any particular artist's work. Instead, the correspondence files must be culled to reveal the wealth of information they contain about his financial affairs, and business endeavors and relationships.
Series I. Alfred Stieglitz: Correspondence, (Boxes 1-97), is organized in three subseries: Personal and Business Correspondence; Family Letters; and Stieglitz-O'Keeffe Letters. The Personal and Business Correspondence is in many ways the heart of the Alfred Stieglitz/Georgia O'Keeffe Archive. This highly comprehensive set of letters, arranged in one alphabetical sequence by correspondent, covers all of the strata in Stieglitz's life, from the leaders of the national and international art and photography communities to his housekeepers and friends from his college days. Two decades of successful efforts to collect letters written by Stieglitz means that readers will find two-way correspondence with a number of individuals. In many cases, Stieglitz's original autograph letters were given to the archive; in others, typed transcripts or photocopies of his letters were made and added to existing carbons from his office files.
Although the quantity and quality of the correspondence quite naturally varies, depending on the relationship between the correspondents and the span of time covered, readers will find a wealth of Stieglitz's opinions and feelings, health and daily activities in these letter sets. Both sides of the correspondence exist for, among others: Ansel Adams, Marie Rapp Boursault, Claude Bragdon, Dorothy Brett, Charles Daniel, F. Holland Day, Arthur Dove, Andrew Droth, William Einstein, Claire Goll, Rebecca Strand James, Margaret Rodakiewicz Kiskadden, Benjamin Kopman, Alfred Kreymborg, Heinrich Kühn, Beatrice Lamb, David Liebovitz, Mabel Dodge Luhan, Stanton MacDonald Wright, Lewis Mumford, Clifford Odets, Ida O'Keeffe, Duncan Phillips, Frederick Ringel, Paul Rosenfeld, Carl Sandburg, Herbert Seligmann, Ettie Stettheimer, Paul Strand, Gerald Sykes, Jennings Tofel, Jean Toomer, Horace Traubel, Edward Weston, and Harold Weston.
Compensating somewhat for the lack of business records elsewhere in the archive, a close reading of these extensive correspondence files also reveals a wealth of information about his business operations and dealings with the galleries and artists which made up the "Stieglitz circle." In a letter to Emma Goldman dated January 8, 1915, Stieglitz wrote of his gallery, 291: "I keep no books, or records of any kind. I have done this to keep the place absolutely free." This statement defines the code of conduct -- a system based on trust and personal responsibility -- by which he operated not only 291 but the other exhibition spaces he furnished for artists over the years. The casual and informal way of handling finances is evident throughout the correspondence files. The exhibition spaces, though very definitely orchestrated by Stieglitz in concept and execution, were run not unlike a cooperative. Rent of the "rooms" was paid from a variety of sources, including donations, percentages taken from sales, or Stieglitz's personal income from investments, and that insurance and off-site storage charges were the artists' responsibility. Exhibitions were installed by Stieglitz, and later, O'Keeffe, with other helpers or sometimes by the artists themselves. A cadre of interested parties would mind the gallery to keep the doors open in addition to the hours that Stieglitz himself spent there, often alone, during his months in New York.
The files also are particularly rich in material that documents the cultural tenor of the time. Many of Stieglitz's correspondents were highly creative people and their letters stand as testimony to their descriptive powers, which extended beyond narratives of events and places to tales concerning the situations they encountered or stories of characters they shared in common. In addition, since Stieglitz's sphere of influence extended into so many "circles," the coverage of art, photography and literary movements is remarkable. Through letters written from the scene, readers can take the pulse of the photographic establishment round the world, including that of Great Britain (in the writings of Annan, Bayley, Coburn, Craigie, Davison, Emerson, Evans, Hinton), Europe (Demachy, Eugene, Kühn, Matthies-Masuren, Steichen, Stouffs) and across America, particularly of Philadelphia (Abbott, Bullock, Stirling, Redfield). The artistic climate of the American Southwest figures prominently in the series through the letters of Dorothy Brett, Rebecca James and Mabel Dodge Luhan, among others. Developments in the West are related by Ansel Adams, Anne Brigman and, in southern California, Stanton MacDonald Wright. The working lives of American writers such as Sherwood Anderson, Clifford Odets and the peripatetic Sadakichi Hartmann are well represented, as are those of American painters at home and abroad, including Thomas Hart Benton, Oscar Bluemner, Arthur Dove, Louis Eilshemius, Marsden Hartley, John Marin, Edward Steichen, and Abraham Walkowitz.
The files are also rich in letters with graphics and other forms of decoration. Several of his correspondents (including Bluemner, Bertram Hartman, Odets, Francis Picabia, Steichen, Walkowitz and Charles Zoler) illustrated their words. Marius DeZayas enclosed sketches for covers of the periodical 291 in a 1915 letter. Others embellished their letters with three-dimensional objects (Anita Pollitzer and Ida O'Keeffe sent feathers and leaves, and O'Keeffe created a special "red letter" edged in scarlet fabric from a quilt she was making at the time). Texas photographer Carlotta Corpron mailed in a set of her own "Equivalents" to show Stieglitz the skies around her home in Denton. Angna Enters sent handmade Christmas and valentine cards. Many wrote on found materials: Zoler used ledger book pages and Hartley, in 1923, the verso of thirty million German marks. Some correspondents' letterhead was distinctively personal: Robert Delaunay's paper was hand-painted, while Ernst Juhl's incorporated a photogravure portrait, and Alfred Langdon Coburn's contained a caricature of him by DeZayas (1908). Mabel Dodge Luhan's letterhead changed dramatically with her move from New York to Taos, though her Los Gallos letterhead does not appear in her own letter files but in those of her visitors, including Rebecca Strand James and Cary Ross.
Technical discussions of photographic matters appear in several of the files, including Eastman Kodak Company, Willis & Clements, F.G. Bruckmann and in Steichen's and Strand's letters. Stieglitz wrote out a chemical formula on the verso of a November 1901 letter from Clarence White, one of several of his notations that appear on the backs of letters throughout the archive. Most of the notes are more mundane and consist of lists of names and numbers (like those on the versos of a George Notman letter and one from Spencer Kellogg to Steichen), menus (on the verso of a draft letter by Picabia to C. Max Jacob) or what appears to be Stieglitz's part of a conversation on the verso of a letter from Alfred Horsley Hinton (which might suggest a case of laryngitis) in mid-September 1904. But substantive scrawl can be found too, such as the design for a Picasso exhibition brochure drawn on the back of a 1911 letter in the file of Rogers and Company.
The scope of the correspondence files is impressive considering the quantity of mail Stieglitz received in places other than New York and the number of times he changed addresses within the city. He retained letters from his daughter's doctors Lefferts and Stanton, and schoolmasters Keller and Veltin. He kept mail from the family's hired help, including Ina Beck, Richard Menshausen, Margaret Prosser, Lewis Putnam and Fred Varnum, and the elevator boy at 291 Fifth Avenue, Thomas Bailey. There are letters from the parents of Sheeler, Steichen and Strand, and a small note from Mary Brown, which is accompanied with a note from O'Keeffe stating that Brown was someone Stieglitz "had a great crush on as a youngster." Letters from friends from Stieglitz's school days in New York include Albert Strauss and Frank "Sime" Herrmann, whose correspondence spans nearly 60 years. Friends from his German school days, described by Stieglitz in a letter to Lewis Mumford as "the finest years of my life," include Karl Bauer, whose file includes a "Zeugnis," or letter of introduction and statement of character, and Hans Totzke. As Stieglitz's sanction meant so much to photographers, particularly regional photographers, many sent their work in for his review. His critiques, including those of W. Edwin Gledhill and F. B. Hodges, were honest and unswayable, even when he was badgered by one as persistent as Chicago photographer Louis Lamb. Another interesting document exists in the correspondence files courtesy of Katharine Rhoades, who sent samples of Stieglitz's handwriting to Brooklyn graphologist Alice Howe, and then enclosed Howe's analysis in her letter of January 15, 1930.
Stieglitz's professional enterprises are documented through letters written by his paid assistants and kindred spirits who conducted business on his behalf, including Marie Boursault, Andrew Droth, William Einstein, Dallett Fuget, Paul Haviland, Dorothy Norman, Cary Ross, Herbert Seligmann, Edward Steichen and Joseph Keiley (who, Stieglitz wrote, in a letter to Herbert French in February 1914, was "one of my very best, probably best, friend I ever had"). Because Stieglitz spent significant amounts of time away from New York, their letters to him serve as activity reports and give the kind of detail that would otherwise have gone unrecorded. Letters from third parties to associates such as Steichen and Keiley, when they were functioning as Stieglitz's agents in his absence, were foldered separately and filed with the writer's other letters to Stieglitz. Similarly, letters written on Stieglitz's behalf by Boursault, Einstein, Norman, and others were treated as letters written by Stieglitz, and are not otherwise noted. Cary Ross, Herbert Seligmann, and others worked as typists for Stieglitz, as did Rebecca Strand James in the early 1920s. Their correspondence reveals that he sent manuscripts to James from Lake George, which she would type and return. As with the galleries and other Stieglitz endeavors, there are no specific files relating to the administration of the Photo-Secession group or any of his periodicals. Three folders of letters and order forms from subscribers to Camera Work were incorporated into the alphabetical sequence to join similar material already filed throughout the series; an undated list of Camera Work subscribers can be found in Box 9, Folder 207.
Hundreds of the letters in the archive are intensely personal in nature. Stanton MacDonald Wright, on July 24, 1920, wrote to Stieglitz that he was "the father confessor to us all," an opinion that was apparently held by many. The archive is populated by minor characters, especially female admirers such as Beatrice Lamb, Frances Levitt and Elsie Stilwell, who wrote volumes about their own lives, and major characters Rebecca James, Ida O'Keeffe and Katharine Rhoades, who did so as well. Some sent their personal poetry, sonnets and paeans: Melville Cane, Helen Freeman, Joseph French, David Litchfield, Sylvan Seligman, Clara Steichen and William Zorach sent verse and free verse along with copious notes on their daily lives and thoughts. Alma Frank and Clara Steichen used Stieglitz as a sounding board, from whom they sought advice and moral support as their marriages were coming undone. Ida O'Keeffe described the elegant house and grounds, and the affluent lifestyle of the Stoeckel family in great detail, in a series of letters written during the summer of 1925, when she worked in their home in Norfolk, Connecticut, as a private nurse.
The Family Letters subseries is primarily letters written to Alfred Stieglitz from his parents, siblings, wife, daughter, grandson, aunts, cousins, nieces and nephews. Boyhood letters from Stieglitz to his parents include a note written to his mother in New Jersey from the Catskills in the summer of 1874, and a letter of December 1877 to his father in which he confesses to telling a lie. There is considerable, often times moving correspondence between Stieglitz and his wife Emmeline and daughter Katherine ("Kitty") Stieglitz Stearns. Emmy's early letters are newsy accounts of her social and daily activities while on vacations in Germany, Paris and other cities in Europe, New Jersey and New England, and provide a good view of the world of upper-middle class leisure and materialism. Her later letters, written a decade after their divorce, are amicable and brief, but poignant, reports of her visits to Kitty, who was institutionalized following the birth of her son in 1923. Letters from Kitty begin with happy juvenile writings and progress through a chronicle of her educational experiences and the dynamic of her parents' breakup, ending with simple notes to her father to thank him for gifts he had sent. Writings from Stieglitz to Emmy and Kitty are few and consist mostly of drafts of letters, including one to Kitty in 1919, written in the form of a book dedication, which was the genesis of a story published as "Who Am I" some twenty years later ( Twice a Year, no. 5-6, 1940-41).
The subseries of Stieglitz-O'Keeffe Letters is divided into three sections: letters written by Stieglitz to O'Keeffe; letters written by O'Keeffe to Stieglitz; and Third-Party Correspondence. The first two sections are arranged in chronological order within each section.
Series II. Alfred Stieglitz: Manuscripts, (Boxes 98-101), is organized in four subseries: Stories by Stieglitz; Writings by Stieglitz; Writings by Others; and Writings by Unidentified Authors. Some of the writings were formerly kept in numbered files of unorganized "Manuscripts." Most were culled directly from the correspondence files, although personal poetry and narratives remained in the files (Hart Crane and Donald Litchfield poems, for example) when they were clearly part of the correspondence.
Stories by Stieglitz contains first-person anecdotal accounts composed by Stieglitz. As evidenced by their correspondence, Stieglitz sent the manuscripts to Rebecca Strand James to be typed. These are separated from Writings by Stieglitz, because they were isolated in earlier arrangements and because an identical set of carbon typescripts was given for the archive by Paul Strand in 1975. Writings by Stieglitz contain the more polished and thoughtful essays as well as a five-page "Journal" from 1873. As with the Stories by Stieglitz, the publication of his essays is unverified.